CURRICULUM VITAE

Joshua J. Timmons, B.S.

PERSONAL

Work Address Boston University, Photonics Center

8 Saint Mary's St, Rm 614, Boston, MA 02215

Home Address 55 South Huntington Ave #103, Boston, MA 02130

Phone +1(941)-720-1396

Email joshuatimmons1@gmail.com

Website joshuatimmons.com

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am interested in studying biological phenomena through simulation paired with laboratory observation. My current research focus is on elucidating mechanisms behind Tumor Treating Fields (TTFields) and Nanosecond Pulsed Electric Fields, both of which have been correlated with a breakdown in tubulin networks. My approach is to use nonequilibrium molecular dynamics to compare the motion of a tubulin model with and without strong external electric fields. Other related interests include image processing, synthetic biology, and software engineering.

EDUCATION

2012 - 2016 B.S. in Biology, Northeastern University, Boston, MA

Bioinformatics Programming, Bioinformatics Methods, Fundamentals of Computer Science, Biological Electron Microscopy, Plant Biotechnology, Biochemistry, Genetics & Molecular Biology, Cell & Molecular Biology, Organic Chemistry, Applied Econometrics, Statistics and Software.

EXPERIENCE

2016 - Present Software Engineer, Lattice Automation Inc., Boston, MA

Building tools for synthetic biologists with Java, Javascript, MongoDB, and Python with an emphasis on combinatorial design, visualization, and

robotic assembly planning.

2014 - Present Research Assistant, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center and Harvard

Medical School, Boston, MA

Screening biomarkers for Glioblastoma multiforme using tissue samples and murine models. Conducting Survival analysis of clinical trial data and patient records in the literature. Building image processing workflows for generating finite element analysis meshes from patient MRIs. Investigating

TTFields' mechanism using nonequilibrium molecular dynamics of highly charged filamentous proteins.

2015 - 2016 Founder and Captain, **iGEM Northeastern**, Boston, MA

Converted microalgae expression plasmids to the BioBrick standard. Created and submitted Nox and Proteorhodopsin iGEM parts for use in microbial fuel cells. Compared of Anderson promoter strengths using GFP fluorescence.

nuorescence.

2013 - 2014 Student Researcher, Northeastern University, Boston, MA

Cultured microbial samples from Greenland. Screened with PCR and MALDI-TOF to understand temporal population changes.

PUBLICATIONS

Refereed Journal Articles

- (5) Ortiz, J., Carr, S.B., Pavan, M., McCarthy, L., **Timmons, J.J.,** & Densmore, D.M. (2017). Automated Robotic Liquid Handling Assembly of Modular DNA Devices. *Journal of Visual Experiments*. Accepted
- (4) **Timmons, J.J.,** Lok, E., San, P., Bui, K., & Wong, E.T. (2017). End-to-End Workflow for Finite Element Analysis of Tumor Treating Fields in Glioblastomas. *Physics in Medicine & Biology*.
- (3) Patnaik, A., Swanson, K.D., Csizmadia, E., Solanki, A., Landon-Brace, N., Gehring, M.P., Helenius, K., Olson, B.M., Pyzer, A.R., Wang, L.C., Elemento, O., Novak, J., Thornley, T.B., Asara, J.M., Montaser, L., **Timmons, J.J.,** Morgan, T.M., Wang, Y., Levantini, E., Clohessy, J.G., Kelly, K., Pandolfi, P.P., Rosenblatt, J.M., Avigan, D.E., Ye, H., Karp, J.M., Signoretti, S., Balk, S.P. & Cantley, L.C. (2017). Cabozantinib eradicates advanced murine prostate cancer by activating anti-tumor innate immunity. *Cancer Discovery*.
- (2) **Timmons, J.J.,** Cohessy, S., & Wong, E.T. (2016). Injection of Syngeneic Murine Melanoma Cells to Determine Their Metastatic Potential in the Lungs. *Journal of Visual Experiments*.
- (1) Wong, E.T., **Timmons, J.J.,** Callahan, A., O'Loughlin, L., Giarusso, B., & Alsop, D.C. (2016). Phase 1 study of low-dose metronomic temozolomide for recurrent malignant gliomas. *BMC Cancer*.

Manuscripts in Submission

(1) **Timmons, J.J.,** Zhang, K., Fong, J., Lok, E., Swanson, K.D., Gautam, S., & Wong, E.T. (2017). Literature Review of Spinal Cord Glioblastoma. *American Journal of Clinical Oncology*. In revision

Conference Proceedings

(5) **Timmons, J.J.,** Pyay, S., Bui, K., Lok, E., & Wong, E.T. (2017). End-to-End Workflow for Finite Element Analysis of Tumor Treating Fields in Glioblastomas. *American Neurological Association*. Oral presentation & poster

- (4) San, P.P., **Timmons, J.J.,** Lok, E., Swanson, K.D., & Wong, E.T. (2016). Analysis of Glioblastoma Physical Characteristics in Patients Benefiting from Tumor Treating Electric Fields Therapy. *Society for Neuro-Oncology*. Poster
- (3) Timmons, J.J. (2015). Therapeutic antibody expression in microalgae. *International Genetically Engineered Machine*. Oral presentation & poster
- (2) Doerfert, S., Berdy, B., Wunschel, E., Sizova, M., **Timmons, J.J.,** Jung, D., Kruppa, G., & Epstein, S. (2014). MALDI-TOF applications for dereplication and identification of environmental microorganisms isolated from Thule, Greenland. *International Society for Microbial Ecology.* Poster
- (1) Berdy, B., Sizova, M., Kaluziak, S., Doerfert, S., Wunschel, E., **Timmons, J.J.,** Jung, D., Torralba, M., Haft, D., Nelson, K., & Epstein, S. (2014). Towards predictable manipulation of microbial communities. *International Society for Microbial Ecology*. Poster

Other Publications

(1) Beal, J., Haddock-Angelli, T., Gershater, M., de Mora., K., Lizarazo, M., Hollenhorst, J., Rettberg, R., & **iGEM Interlab Study Contributors.** (2016). Reproducibility of Fluorescent Expression from Engineered Biological Constructs in E. coli. *PlosOne*.

AWARDS AND FUNDING

2016	University Honors Program Distinction
2016	Advanced Research and Creative Endeavor Award, \$3,000
2015 - 2016	iGEM Northeastern College and Department Fundraising, \$15,000
2015 - 2016	iGEM Northeastern Corporate Fundraising, \$1,600
2015	Above & Beyond CEP Award
2012 - 2016	Northeastern National Merit Scholarship, \$42,000/year
2012 - 2016	UPS Foundation National Merit Scholarship, \$6,000/year

LEADERSHIP AND MENTORING

2014	TA and Mentor, Northeastern Honors Mentors Program
2015	Peer Mentor, Northeastern Peer Program
2013 - 2016	President, Editor, and Writer, NUScience Magazine
2015 - 2016	Founder and Captain, Northeastern iGEM Team

SOFTWARE SKILLS

Operating Systems Fedora Linux, Ubuntu Linux, Windows, MacOS

Languages Java, Python, JavaScript, TCL, MATLAB, R, Perl, Golang

Databases MongoDB, MySQL

Applications and Amazon Web Services, NAMD, VMD, R Studio, Bash, Git, Benchling,

Services Node, NPM, Vaadin, Adobe Illustrator, CircleCI, GraphQL

LABORATORY SKILLS

General Western blot, ELISA, PCR, microbial culturing, tissue culturing,

MALDI-TOF, Bradford assay, DNA extraction, DNA electrophoresis,

DNA purification

Synthetic Biology Gibson assembly, MoClo assembly, restriction digest, transformation

Mouse Handling Intraperitoneal injection, tail vein injection, osmotic pump surgery

Imaging Transmission electron microscopy, scanning electron microscopy